Bryant, S.D. Union Congregational Church Records, 1892-2009.
Congregational Library & Archives
Bryant, S.D. Union Congregational Church, 1892-2009.
RG5431
Congregational Library & Archives
1.49 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes, 1 folder)
The Union Congregational Church of Bryant, S.D. was founded on March 13, 1892, with the writing of it's first constitution. On March 30th, 1892, the church joined in covenant fellowship with Congregational churches in DeSmet, Hetland, Erwin, Lake Preston, and Willow Lakes. The church building was finished in 1897 and later remodeled in 1945. This collection records the activities of the church and it's community through annual reports, membership records, church correspondence, yearbook reports, and financial records.
Brewton, Marjie
Union Congregational Church (Bryant, S.D.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Rev. Marjie Brewton in February 2022; Accession 2022-02.
Historical Note
The Union Congregational Church of Bryant, South Dakota, was founded on March 13, 1892, with the writing of its first constitution. On March 30th, 1892, the church joined in covenant fellowship with Congregational churches in DeSmet, Hetland, Erwin, Lake Preston, and Willow Lake. The congregation originally met for worship in the Baptist church and other places until a church building was financed and built in 1897. In 1945 a building fund was established to remodel the Church, and a basement was later dug and bricked. In 1911, the church voted to separate from the Congregational Home Mission Board and become financially self-supporting. From 1929 to 1943, the church struggled with both finances and attendance, and until 1984 struggled to keep pastors employed. As a result of this, the church shared several pastors with the Willow Lake Congregational Church from 1946 to 1987. The church was part of the United Church of Christ. In 1993, the Prairie Retreat, a nonprofit led by Rev. Marjie Brewton, was sponsored by the church and ran as an extended ministry. The church was dissolved in 2020.
Scope and Contents
The Bryant, S.D. Union Congregational Church records include annual reports, membership records, church correspondence, and yearbook reports. Also included are financial records, in the form of ledgers, receipts, treasurer's records, and building records.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in chronological order with closely related materials grouped together as appropriate.
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church correspondence.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Clergy -- Resignation.; Constitutions.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Obituaries.; Sunday schools.; Women in church work.; Bryant (S.D.) -- Church history.; Union Congregational Church (Bryant, S.D.)
- Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1892 1924; 1892-1924 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Separated Materials
  Material was removed from this volume and made into the folder titled "Letter of Resignation, 1924."
- Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1924 1956; 1924-1956 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  Material was removed from this volume and made into the folder titled "Materials from the Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1924-1956."
- Materials from Union Congregational Annual Report, 1924 1956; 1924-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This material was removed from the Union Congregational Annual Report, 1924-1956.
- Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1956 2004; 1956-2004 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  Material was removed from this volume and made into the folder titled "Materials from the Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1956-2004."
- Materials from Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1956 2004; 1956-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This Material was removed from the Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1956-2004.
- Building Records, 1897 2009; 1897-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sabbath Reading, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- International Sunday School Association Certificate, 1913 (Folder 1)
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1918 1944; 1918-1944 (Box 1, Volume 4)
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1918 1950; 1918-1950 (Box 1, Volume 5)
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1945 1952; 1945-1952 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Material was removed from this volume and made into the folder titled "Materials from Treasurer's Record Books, 1945-1952."
- Materials from Treasurer's Record Books, 1945 1952; 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This Material was removed from the volume "Treasurer's Record Books, 1945-1952."
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1953 1958; 1953-1958 (Box 2, Volume 2)
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1958 1961; 1958-1961 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  Material was removed from this item and made into the folder titled "Materials from Treasurer's Record Books, 1958-1961."
- Materials from Treasurer's Record Books, 1958 1961; 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This material was removed from the volume "Treasurer's Record Books, 1958-1961."
- Treasurer's Record Books, 1962 1973; 1962-1973 (Box 1, Volume 7)
- Letter of Resignation, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This material was removed from the volume "Union Congregational Annual Reports, 1892-1924."
- Correspondence, 1938 1992; 1938-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Yearbook Reports, 1939 1983; 1939-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Membership Papers, 1940 1978; 1940-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Anniversary Books and Constitutions, 1964 1996; 1964-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  The volume "'Heart of the Earth', 1989." was removed from this folder.
- Sunday School Secretary's Records, 1971 1975; 1971-1975 (Box 1, Volume 8)
- "Heart of the Earth", 1989 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  This material was removed from the folder titled "Anniversary Books and Constitutions, 1964-1996."
- Women in Mission, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Donations "in Memorium", undated (Box 2, Folder 1)